A Guide to the Militia Lists of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1779-1782
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Militia Lists of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1779-1782
The Library of Virginia
APA 225
1 box
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession APA 225, Transferred prior to 1905.
Biographical Information
Although the Virginia militia was organized officially by Governor Thomas Dale in 1611, in reality the colonists had been organized for their mutual defense against hostile Indians and Europeans since establishing Jamestown in 1607. As the colony grew and counties were formed, the House of Burgesses refined the organization of the militia, which was under the authority of the governor. By the time the revolutionary war began, the militia had been structured along English lines, with regiments in each county commanded by a county lieutenant holding the rank of colonel.
To ensure "conformity in their exercise and evolutions, so that when the different battalions join in brigades there may be no mistake or confusion," the third revolutionary convention passed an ordinance at its session begun on July 17, 1775, establishing the Office of the Adjutant General. Both the office and the trend toward uniformity continued after the war. The Civil War marked the end of the militia system of 250 years.
Scope and Content
This series consists of a collection of revolutionary war militia lists. These payroll lists generally include the name of the company and county, and record the names of the men in the militia, number of days in service and/or amount of pay, and may also include remarks. Militia lists for Henry County (List of recruits) and Loudoun County also record the soldiers' occupations, heights, and place of residence. Also includes commissioner's accounts, lists of recruits and lists of classes (with amount of tax).
Lists are included for the following counties: Albemarle, Amelia, Amherst, Caroline, Essex, Fauquier, Fredrick, Gloucester, Henry, King George, Loudoun, New Kent, Prince William, Rockbridge, Rockingham, Shenandoah, Washington, and Westmoreland.
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical order by county.
Contents List
- Militia Lists, 1779-1782.
  - Albemarle County (Captain Benjamin Harris' Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amelia County (Commanded by Edward Hunter, Lt. Pressley Gates' Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amherst County (Capt. Azariah Martin's Company), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amherst County (Capt. William Tucker's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Caroline County (Capt. Edward Jones' Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Essex County, 1781. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fauquier County (Capt. John Ball's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fauquier County (Capt. William Triplett's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Frederick County (Capt. Samuel Glass' Company), undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Frederick County (Col. David Kennedy's Battalion, 1781. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gloucester County (Capt. Thomas Baytop's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gloucester County (Capt. Thomas Billup's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Henry County (Capt. David Carlin's Company), 1779. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Henry County (Capt. David Carlin's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Henry County (List of recruits), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - King George County (List of recruits), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loudoun County (Capt. Henry McCabe's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loudoun County (Capt. Samuel A. Noland's Company), 1782. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loudoun County (Size Roll of recruits), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New Kent County (List of classes), 1782. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Prince William County (List of recruits), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rockbridge County (Capt. James Gilmore's Company), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rockingham County (Capt. George Baxter's Company), 1782. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rockingham County (List of recruits), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Shenandoah County (Capt. Linefield Sharpe's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Shenandoah County (List of recruits), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Shenandoah County (List of recruits), 1782. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Washington County (Lt. Reece Bowen's Company), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Washington County (Capt. David Beatie's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Washington County (Ensign Robert McFarland's Company), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Washington County (Capt. James Dysart's Company), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Westmoreland County (List of recruits), 1780. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Westmoreland County (Commissioner's accounts), 1781. (Box 1, Folder 17)